DAVID SONTAG: Today
we'll be talking
about risk stratification.
After giving you
a broad overview
of what I mean by
risk stratification,
we'll give you a
case study which
you read about in your
readings for today's lecture
coming from early detection
of type 2 diabetes.
And I won't be, of course,
repeating the same material you
read about it in your readings.
Rather I'll be giving
some interesting color
around what are some of
the questions that we need
to be thinking about as
machine learning people
when we try to apply machine
learning to problems like this.
Then I'll talk about
some of the subtleties.
What can go wrong with machine
learning based approaches
to risk stratification?
And finally, the last
half of today's lecture
is going to be a discussion.
So about 3:00 PM, you'll see
a man walk through the door.
His name is Leonard D'Avolio.
He is a professor at
Brigham Women's Hospital.
He also has a startup
company called
Sift, which is
working on applying
risk stratification now, and
they have lots of clients.
So they've been really
deep in the details
of how to make this stuff work.
And so we'll have an interview
between myself and him,
and we'll have
opportunity for all of you
to ask questions as well.
And that's what I hope will
be the most exciting part
of today's lecture.
Then going on beyond
today's lecture,
we're now in the beginning of
a sequence of three lectures
on very similar topics.
So next Thursday,
we'll be talking
about survival modeling.
And you can think about it as
an extension of today's lecture,
talking about what you should
do if your data has centering,
which I'll define
for you shortly.
Although today's
lecture is going
to be a little bit
more high level,
next Thursday's
lecture is where we're
going to really start to get
into mathematical details
about how one should
tackle machine learning
problems with centered data.
And then the following
lecture after that
is going to be on
physiological data,
and that lecture will also be
much more technical in nature
compared to the first couple
of weeks of the course.
So what is risk stratification?
At a high level, you think
about risk stratification
as a way of taking in
the patient population
and separating out
all of your patients
into one of two or
more categories.
Patients with high
risk, patients
with low risk,
and maybe patients
somewhere in the middle.
Now the reason why we might
want to do risk stratification
is because we
usually want to try
to act on those predictions.
So the goals are
often one of coupling
those predictions with
known interventions.
So for example, patients
in the high risk
pool-- we will attempt to do
something for those patients
to prevent whatever that outcome
is of interest from occurring.
Now risk stratification is
quite different from diagnosis.
Diagnosis often has very,
very stringent criteria
on performance.
If you do a mis-diagnosis
of something,
that can have very
severe consequences
in terms of patients being
treated for conditions
that they didn't need
to be treated for,
and patients dying because they
were not diagnosed in time.
Risk stratification you
think of as a little bit
more fuzzy in nature.
We want to do our best job
of trying to push patients
into each of these categories--
high risk, low risk, and so on.
And as I'll show you
throughout today's lecture,
the performance characteristics
that we'll often care about
are going to be a bit different.
We're going to look a
bit more at quantities
such as positive
predictive value.
Of the patients we say are high
risk, what fraction of them
are actually high risk?
And in that way, it differs
a bit from diagnosis.
Also as a result of the
goals being different,
the data that's used is
often very different.
In risk stratification, often we
use data which is very diverse.
So you might bring in
multiple views of a patient.
You might use auxiliary data
such as patients' demographics,
maybe even socioeconomic
information
about a patient, all of which
very much affect their risk
profiles but may not be used
for a unbiased diagnosis
of the patient.
And finally in today's
economic environment,
risk stratification
is very much targeted
towards reducing cost of
the US health care setting.
And so I'll give you
a few examples of risk
stratification, some of which
have cost as a major goal
others which don't.
The first example is that
of predicting an infant's
risk of severe morbidity.
So this is a premature baby.
My niece, for example, was
born three months premature.
It was really scary for my
sister and my whole family.
And the outcomes of patients
who are born premature
have really changed dramatically
over the last century.
And now patients who are
born three months premature,
like my niece, actually can
survive and do really well
in terms of long term outcomes.
But of the many
different inventions
that led to these improved
outcomes, one of them
was having a very good
understanding of how risky
a particular infant might be.
So a very common
score that's used
to try to characterize
risk for infant birth,
generally speaking, is
known as the Apgar score.
For example when
my son was born,
I was really excited when
a few seconds after my son
was delivered, the nurse
took out a piece of paper
and computed the Apgar score.
I studied that, really
interesting, right?
And then I got back to some
other things that I had to do.
But that score isn't actually
as accurate as it could be.
And there is this
paper, which we'll
talk about in a week and a
half, by Suchi Saria who's
a professor at Johns Hopkins,
which looked at how one could
use a machine learning based
approach to really improve
our ability to predict
morbidity in infants.
Another example,
which I'm pulling
from the readings for today's
lecture, has to do with--
for patients who come
into the emergency
department with a heart related
condition, try to understand
do they need to be admitted
to the coronary care unit?
Or is it safe enough to
let that patient go home
and be managed by
their primary care
physician or their cardiologist
outside of the hospital
setting?
Now that paper, you might have
all noticed, was from 1984.
So this isn't a new concept.
Moreover, if you look
at the amount of data
that they used in that study,
it was over 2,000 patients.
They had a nontrivial number
of variables, 50 something
variables.
And they used a non-trivial
machine learning algorithm.
They used logistic regression
with a feature selection
built in to prevent themselves
from over fitting to the data.
And the goal there was
very much cost oriented.
So the premise was that
if one could quickly
decide these patients
who've just come to the ER
are not high risk and
we could send them home,
then we'll be able to reduce the
large amount of cost associated
with those admissions
to coronary care units.
And the final example
I'll give right now
is that of predicting likelihood
of hospital readmission.
So this is something which is
getting a real lot of attention
in the United States health care
space over the last few years
because of penalties which
the US government has imposed
on hospitals who have a
large number of patients who
have been released
from the hospital,
and then within the next 30
days readmitted to the hospital.
And that's part
of the transition
to value based care, which Pete
mentioned in earlier lectures.
And so the premise is that
there are many patients who
are hospitalized but are
not managed appropriately
on discharge or after discharge.
For example, maybe this patient
who has a heart condition
wasn't really clear
on what they should
have done when they go home.
For example, what medications
should they be taking?
When should they follow up
with their cardiologist?
What things they should
be looking out for,
in terms of warning
signs that they
should go back to the hospital
or call their doctor for.
And as a result of that
poor communication,
it's conjectured that these
poor outcomes might occur.
So if we could figure
out which of the patients
are likely to have
those readmissions,
and if we could predict that
while the patients are still
in the hospital, then
we could change the way
that discharge is done.
For example, we could send
a nurse or a social worker
to talk to the patient.
Go really slowly through
the discharge instructions.
Maybe after the
patient is discharged,
one could have a nurse
follow up at the patient's
home over the next few weeks.
And in this way, hopefully
reduce the likelihood
of that readmission.
So at a high level, there's
the old versus the new.
And this is going to be really
a discussion throughout the rest
of today's lecture.
What's changed since
that 1984 article which
you read for today's readings?
Well, the traditional approaches
to risk stratification
are based on scoring systems.
So I mentioned to you
a few minutes ago,
the Apgar scoring
system is shown here.
You're going to say for each
of these different correct
criteria-- activity,
pulse, grimace, appearance,
respiration--
you look at the baby, and you
say well, activity is absent.
Or maybe they're
active movement.
Appearance might be pale or
blue, which would get 0 points,
or completely pink
which gets 2 points.
And for each one
of these answers,
you add up the
corresponding points.
You get a total
number of points.
And you look over
here and you say, OK,
well if you have
a 0 to 3 points,
the baby is at severe risk.
If they have 7 to 10 points,
then the baby is low risk.
And there are hundreds of
such scoring rules which
have been very carefully
derived through studies not
dissimilar to the one that
you read for today's readings,
and which are actually widely
used in the health care system
today.
But the times have been
changing quite rapidly
in the last 5 to 10 years.
And now, what most of the
industry is moving towards
are machine learning
based methods
that can work with a much higher
dimensional set of features
and solve a number
of key challenges
of these early approaches.
First-- and this is perhaps
the most important aspect,
they can fit more easily
into clinical workflows.
So the scores I
showed you earlier
are often done manually.
So one has to think
to do the score.
One has to figure out what
the corresponding inputs are.
And as a result of
that, often they're
not used as frequently
as they should be.
Second, the new machine
learning approaches
can get higher
accuracy potentially,
due to their ability to
use many more features
than the traditional pitches.
And finally, they can be
much quicker to drive.
So all of the traditional
scoring systems
had a very long research
and development process
that led to their adoption.
First, you gather the data.
Then you build the models.
Then you check the models.
Then you do an evaluation
in one hospital.
Then you do a prospective
evaluation in many hospitals.
And each one of those
steps takes a lot of time.
Now with these machine
learning based approaches,
it raises the possibility of
a research assistant sitting
in a hospital, or in a
computer science department,
saying oh, I think it would
be really useful to derive
a score for this problem.
You take data that's available.
You apply your machine
learning algorithm.
And even if it's a condition
or an outcome which
occurs very infrequently,
if you have access
to a large enough
data set you'll
be able to get enough
samples in order
to actually predict that
somewhat very narrow outcome.
And so as a result, it
really opens the door
to rethinking about the way
that risk stratification can
be used.
But as a result, there
are also new dangers
that are introduced.
And we'll talk about some
of those in today's lecture,
and we'll continue
to talk about those
in next Thursday's lecture.
So these models are being
widely commercialized.
Here is just an example
from one of many companies
that are building risk
stratification tools.
This is from Optum.
And what I'm showing
you here is the output
from one of their models
which is predicting
COPD related hospitalizations.
And so you'll see that this
is a population level view.
So for all of the
patients who are
of interest to that hospital,
they will score the patient--
using either one of
the scores I showed you
earlier, the manual ones, or
maybe a machine learning based
model--
and they'll be put into one
of these different categories
depending on the risk level.
And then one can dig in deeper.
So for example, you could
click on one of those buckets
and try to see well, who
are the patients that
are highest at risk.
And what are some potentially
impactible aspects
of those patients' health?
Here, I'm showing you for a
slightly different problem
that are predicting high
risk diabetes patients.
And you see that
for each patient,
we're listing the
number of A1C tests,
the value of the last A1C test,
the day that it was performed.
And in this way, you could
notice oh, this patient
is at high risk of
having diabetes.
But look, they haven't
been tracking their A1C.
Maybe they have
uncontrolled diabetes.
Maybe we need to get
them into the clinic,
get their blood tested,
see whether maybe they
need a change in
medication, and so on.
So in this way, we can
stratify the patient population
and think about
interventions that can be
done for that subset of them.
So I'll move now into a case
study of early detection
of type 2 diabetes.
The reason why this
problem is of importance
is because it's
estimated that there
are 25% of patients with
undiagnosed type 2 diabetes
in the United States.
And that number is
equally large as you
go to many other
countries internationally.
So if we can find patients who
currently have diabetes or are
likely to develop
diabetes in the future,
then we could attempt
to impact them.
So for example, we could
develop new interventions
that can prevent those
patients from worsening
in their diabetes progression.
For example, weight loss
programs or getting patients
on first line diabetic
treatments like Metformin.
But the key problem which
I'll be talking about today
is really, how do you find
that at risk population?
So the traditional
approach to doing that
is very similar to
that Apgar score.
This is a scoring
system used in Finland
which asks a series of
questions and has points
associated with each answer.
So what's the age
of the patient?
What's their body mass index?
Do they eat vegetables, fruit?
Have they ever taken anti
hypertension medication?
And so on, and you get a
final score out, right?
Lower than 7 would
be 1 in 100 risk
of developing type 2 diabetes.
Higher than 20 is
very high risk.
1 in 2 people will
develop type 2 diabetes
in the next 10 years.
But as I mentioned,
these scores haven't
had the impact that we had
hoped that they might have.
And the reason really
is because they
haven't been actually
used nearly as much
as they should be.
So what we will be
thinking through is,
can we change the way in which
risk stratification is done?
Rather than it having
to be something which
is manually done, when
you think to do it,
we can make it now
population wide.
We could, for example,
take data that's
already available from
a health insurance
company, use machine learning.
Maybe we don't have access
to all of those features
I showed you earlier.
Maybe we don't know
the patient's weight,
but we will use machine
learning on the data
that we do have to try
to find other surrogates
of those things we
don't have, which
might predict diabetes risk.
And then we can apply
it automatically
behind the scenes for
millions of different patients
and find the high
risk population
and perform interventions
for those patients.
And by the way, the work that
I'm telling you about today
is work that really came
out of my lab's research
in the last few years.
So this is an example going
back to the set of stakeholders,
which we talked about
in the first lecture.
This is an example of
a risk stratification
being done at the payer level.
So the data which is going
to be used for this problem
is administrative data,
data that you typically find
in health insurance companies.
So I'm showing you here a single
patient's timeline and the type
of data that you
would expect to be
available for that
patient across time.
In red, it's showing
their eligibility records.
When had they been enrolled
in that health insurance?
And that's really important,
because if they're not
enrolled in the health
insurance on some month,
then the lack of
data for that patient
isn't because nothing happened.
It's because we just don't
have visibility into it.
It's missing.
In green, I'm showing
medical claims which
are associated with
diagnosis codes
that Pete talked
about last week,
procedure codes, CPT codes.
We know what the specialist
was that the patient went
to see, like cardiologists,
primary care physician,
and so on.
We know where the
service was performed,
and we know when
it was performed.
And then from pharmacy, we have
access to medication records
shown in the top right there.
We know what medication
was prescribed,
and we have it coded
to the NDC code--
National Drug Code, which
Pete talked about again
last Tuesday.
We know the number
of days' supply
of the medication, the number
of refills that are available
still, and so on.
And finally, we have
access to laboratory tests.
Now traditionally, health
insurance companies
only know what
tests were performed
because they have to pay for
that test to be performed.
But more and more, health
insurance companies
are forming partnerships
with companies
like Quest and LabCorps to
actually get access also
to the results of
those lab tests.
And in the data set that
I'll tell you about today,
we actually do have those
lab test results as well.
So what are these elements
for this population?
This population comes
from Philadelphia.
So if we look at the
top diagnosis codes,
for example, we'll see that
of 135,000 patients who
had laboratory data,
there were over 400,000
different diagnosis
codes for hypertension.
You'll notice that's greater
than the number of people.
That's because they occurred
multiple times across time.
Other common diagnosis codes
included hyperlipidemia,
hypertension, type 2 diabetes.
And you'll notice that
there's actually quite a bit
of interesting detail here.
Even in diagnosis codes,
you'll find things
that sound more like
symptoms-- like fatigue,
which is over here.
Or you also have records of
procedures, in many cases.
Like they got a
vaccination for influenza.
Here's another example.
This is now just
telling you something
about the broad statistics
of laboratory tests
in this population.
Creatinine, potassium,
glucose, liver enzymes
are all the most
popular lab tests.
And that's not surprising,
because often there
is a panel called the CBC
panel which is what you would
get in your annual physical.
And that has many of these
top laboratory test results.
But then as you look
down into the tail,
there are many other
laboratory test results that
are more specialized in nature.
For example,
hemoglobin A1C is used
to track roughly 3 month
average of blood glucose
and is used to understand a
patient's diabetes status.
So that's just to give
you a sense of what
is the data behind the scenes.
Now let's think, how
do we really derive--
how do we tackle--
how do we formulate this
risk stratification problem
as a machine learning problem?
Well today, I'll give you one
example of how to formulate it
as a machine learning problem.
But in Tuesday's lecture, I'll
tell you several other ways.
Here, we're going to
think about a reduction
to binary classification.
We're going to go back in time.
We're going to pretend
it's January 1, 2009.
We're going to say suppose
that we had run this risk
stratification algorithm on
every single patient on January
1, 2009.
We're going to
construct features
from the data in the past,
so the past few years.
We're going to predict
something about the future.
And there many things
you could attempt
to predict about the future.
I'm showing you here 3
different prediction tasks
corresponding to
different gaps--
a 0 year gap, a 1 year
gap, and a 2 year gap.
And for each one
of these, it asks
will the patient newly
develop type 2 diabetes
in that prediction window?
So for example, for
this prediction task
we're going to exclude patients
who have developed type 2
diabetes between 2009 and 2011.
And we're only going to count
as positives patients who
get newly diagnosed with type 2
diabetes between 2011 and 2013.
And one of the
reasons why you might
want to include a
gap in the model
is because often,
there's label leakage.
So if you look at
the very top set up,
often what happens
is a clinician
might have a really good
idea that the patient might
be diabetic, but it's not
yet coded in a way which
our algorithms can pick up.
And so on January 1,
2009 the primary care
physician for the patient might
be well aware that this patient
is diabetic, might already
be doing interventions
based on it.
But our algorithm
doesn't know that,
and so that patient,
because of the signals that
are present in the
data, is going to
at the very top of
our prediction list.
We're going to say
this patient is someone
you should be going after.
But that's really not
an interesting patient
to be going after, because
the clinicians are probably
already doing interventions that
are relevant for that patient.
Rather, we want to find the
patients where the diabetes
might be more unexpected.
And so this is one of the
subtleties that really arises
when you try to use
retrospective clinical data
to derive your labels to
use within machine learning
for risk stratification.
So in the result
I'll tell you about,
I'm going to use a 1 year gap.
Another problem is that the
data is highly censored.
So what I mean by
censoring is that we often
don't have full visibility
into the data for a patient.
For example, patients
might have only come
into the health insurance in
2013, and so January 1, 2009
we have no data on them.
They didn't even exist
in the system at all.
So there are two
types of censoring.
One type of censoring is
called left censoring.
It means when we don't
have data to the left,
for example in the feature
construction window.
Another type of censoring
is called right censoring.
It means when we don't
have data about the patient
to the right of that time line.
And for each one of
these in our work
here, we tackle it
in a different way.
For left centering, we're
going to deal with it.
We're going to say OK, we might
have limited data on patients.
But we will use whatever data is
available from the past 2 years
in order to make
our predictions.
And for patients who have less
data available, that's fine.
We have sort of a more
sparse feature vector.
For right centering,
it's a little bit more
challenging to deal with
in this binary reduction,
because if you don't
know what the label is,
it's really hard to use
within, for example,
a supervised machine
learning approach.
In Tuesday's lecture,
I'll talk about a way
to deal with right censoring.
In today's lecture, we're
going to just ignore it.
And the way that
we'll ignore it is
by changing the inclusion
and exclusion criteria.
We will exclude patients for
whom we don't know the label.
And to be clear, that could
be really problematic.
So for example, imagine if you
go back to this picture here.
Imagine that we're
in this scenario.
And imagine that if we only have
data on a patient up to 2011,
we remove them from
the data set, OK?
Because we don't have full
visibility into the 2010
to 2012 time window.
Well, suppose that exactly
the day before the patient
was going to be removed
from the data set--
right before the data
disappears for the patient
because, for example, they
might change health insurers--
they were diagnosed
with type 2 diabetes.
And maybe the reason
why they changed
health insurers had
to do with them being
diagnosed with type 2 diabetes.
Then we've excluded that
patient from the population,
and we might be really biasing
the results of the model,
by now taking away a whole
set of the population
where this model would've been
really important to apply.
So thinking about how you really
do this inclusion exclusion
and how that changes the
generalizability of the model
you get is something that should
be at the top of your mind.
So the machine
learning algorithm
used in that paper
which you've read
is L1 regularized
logistic regression.
One of the reasons for using L1
regularized logistic regression
is because it provides a way to
use a high dimensional feature
set.
But at the same time, it allows
one to do feature selection.
So I'll go more into detail
on that in just a moment.
All of you should be familiar
with the idea of formulating
machine learning as an
optimization problem
where you have
some loss function,
and you have some
regularization term--
w, in this case, as the
weights of your linear model,
which we're trying to learn.
For those of you who've seen
support vector machines before,
support vector machines
will use what's
called L2 regularization
where we'll
be putting a penalty on the
L2 norm of the weight vector.
Instead, what we
did in this paper
is used L1 regularization.
So this penalty is
defined over here.
It's summing over the
features and looking
at the absolute value
for each of the weights
and summing those up.
So one of the reasons
why L1 regularization has
what's known as a
sparsity benefit
can be explained
by this picture.
So this is just a
demonstration by sketch.
Suppose that we're trying
to solve this optimization
problem here.
So this is the level set
of your loss function.
It's a quadratic function.
And suppose that
instead of adding
on your regularization
as a second term
to your optimization
problem, you were
to instead put in a constraint.
So you might say we're
going to minimize
the loss subject to the L1
norm of your weight vector
being less than 3.
Well, then what I'm showing
you here is weight space.
I'm showing you 2 dimensions.
This x-axis is weight 1.
This y-axis is weight 2.
And if you put an L1
constraint-- for example,
you said that the sum of the
absolute values of weight 1
and weight 2 have
to be equal to 1--
then the solution space has
to be along this diamond.
On the other hand, if you put
an L2 constraint on your weight
vector, then it would correspond
to this feasibility space.
For example, this
would say something
like the L2 norm over the weight
vector has to be equal to 1.
So it would be a ball,
saying that the radius has
to always be equal to 1.
So suppose now you're
trying to minimize
that objective function,
subject to the solution having
to be either on the ball, which
is what you would do if you
were optimizing the L2 norm,
versus living on this diamond,
which is what would happen if
you're optimizing the L1 norm.
Well, the optimal
solution is going
to be in essence
the closest point
along the circle,
which gets as close as
possible to the middle
of that level set.
So over here, the
closest point is that 1.
And you'll see that this point
has a non-zero w1 and w2.
Over here, the closest
point is over here.
Notice that has a zero value of
w1 and a non-zero value of w2,
thus it's found a sparser
solution than this one.
So this is just to give you
some intuition about why
using L1 regularization
results in sparse solutions
to your optimization problem.
And that could be
beneficial for two purposes.
First, it can help prevent
over fitting in settings
where there exists a very
good risk model that uses
a small number of features.
And to point out,
that's not a crazy idea
that there might exist
a risk model that
uses a small number
of features, right?
Remember, think back
to that Apgar score
or the FINDRISC, which was used
to predict diabetes in Finland.
Each of those had only
5 to 20 questions.
And based on the answers
to those 5 to 20 questions,
one could get a pretty good
idea of what the risk is
of that patient, right?
So the fact that there might
be a small number of features
that are together
sufficient is actually
a very reasonable prior.
And it's one reason why L1
regularization is actually
very well suited to these types
of risk stratification problems
on this type of data.
The second reason is
one of interpretability.
If one wants to
then ask, well, what
are the features that actually
were used by this model
to make predictions?
When you find only
20 or a few features,
you can enumerate all of them
and look to see what they are.
And in that way,
understand what is
going on into the
predictions that are made.
And that also has
a very big impact
when it comes to translation.
So suppose you built a model
using data from this health
insurance company.
And this health
insurance company
just happened to have access
to a huge number of features.
But now you want to go somewhere
else and apply the same model.
If what you've
learned is a model
with only a few
hundred features,
you're able to dwindle it down.
Then it provides an opportunity
to deploy your model much more
easily.
The next place you
go to, you only
need to get access
to those features
in order to make
your predictions.
So I'll finish up in
the next 5 minutes
in order to get to our
discussion with Leonard.
But I just want to recap
what are the features that
go into this model, and what
are some of the valuations
that we use.
So the features
that we used here
were ones that were
designed to take
into consideration that
there is a lot of missing
data for patients.
So rather than think through
do we impute this feature,
do we not impute this
feature, we simply look to see
were these features
ever observed?
So we choose our
feature space in order
to already account for the fact
that there's a lot missing.
For example, we look to see
what types of specialists
has this doctor seen in the
past, been to in the past?
For every possible
specialist, we put a 1
in the corresponding
dimension if the patient
has seen that type of
specialist and 0 otherwise.
For the top 1,000 most
common medications,
we look to see has the patient
ever taken his medication,
yes or no?
And again, 0 or 1 in the
corresponding dimension.
For laboratory
tests, that's where
we do something which is
a little bit different.
We look to see, first of
all, was a laboratory test
ever administered?
And then we say OK, if
it was administered,
was the result ever low, out
of bounds on the lower side?
Was the result ever high?
Was the result ever normal?
Is the value increasing?
Is the value decreasing?
Is the value fluctuating?
I noticed that each
one of these quantities
is well-defined,
even for patients
who don't ever have
any laboratory test
results available, right?
The answer would be 0, it
was never administered.
And 0, it was never low.
0, it was never high, and so on.
OK?
AUDIENCE: Is the
value increasing?
Is it every time, or
how do you define?
DAVID SONTAG: So
increasing here--
first of all, if there
is only a single value
observed then it's 0.
If there were at least 2 values
observed, then you look to see
was there ever any adjacent
pair of observations
where the second one was
higher than the first one?
That's the way it
was defined here.
AUDIENCE: Then it has
increased and then decreased.
You put 1 and 1 on
the [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID SONTAG: Correct.
That's what we did here.
And it's extremely
simple, right?
So there are lots of better
ways that you could do this.
And in fact, this
is an example which
we'll come back to perhaps a
little bit in the next lecture
and then more in
subsequent lectures when
we talk about using recurrent
neural networks to try
to summarize time series data.
Because one could imagine
that using such an approach
could actually automatically
learn such features.
AUDIENCE: Just to double
check, is fluctuating one
of the other two [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID SONTAG: Fluctuating
is exactly the scenario
that was just described.
It can go up, and
then it goes down.
Has to do both, yeah.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: It said in the first
question, [INAUDIBLE] together.
Was the test ever
administered [INAUDIBLE]??
And the value you
have there is 1.
DAVID SONTAG: Correct.
So indeed, there is a
huge amount of correlation
between these features.
If any of these were 1, then
this is also going to be 1.
AUDIENCE: Especially
the results.
DAVID SONTAG: Yeah,
but you would still
want to include this 1 in here.
So imagine that all
of these were 0.
You don't know if they're 0
because these things didn't
happen or because the
test was never performed.
AUDIENCE: Are the
low, high, normal--
DAVID SONTAG: They're just
binary indicators here, right?
AUDIENCE: Doesn't it have
to fit into one category?
DAVID SONTAG: Well, no.
Oh, I see what you're saying.
So you're saying if the
result was ever present,
then it would be at
least 1 of these 3.
Maybe.
It gets into some of the
technical details which
I don't remember right now.
It was a good question.
And this is the next most
really important detail.
The way I just
described this, there
was no notion of time in that.
But of course when
these things happened
can be really important.
So the next thing we
do is we re-compute
all of these features for
different time buckets.
So we compute them for the
last 6 months of history,
for the last 24
months of history,
and then for all of
the past history.
And we can catenate together
all of those feature vectors
and what you get out.
In this case, it was
something like a 42,000
dimensional feature vector.
By the way, it's 42,000
dimensional and not higher
because the features that
we used for diagnosis codes
for this paper were
not temporal in nature.
And one could easily
make them temporal
in nature, in which case it'd
be more like 60,000 features.
I'm going to skip over
the deriving labels
and get back to that next time.
I just want to briefly
talk about how does one
evaluate these types of models.
And I'll give you one
view on evaluations,
and shortly we'll hear a
very different type of view.
So here, what I'm showing
you are the variables
that have been selected by the
model and have non-zero weight.
So for example, the very top you
see impaired fasting glucose,
which is used by the model.
It's not surprising
because we're
trying to predict is the
patient likely to develop type
2 diabetes.
Now you might ask, if a
patient has a diagnosis
code for impaired
fasting glucose
aren't they already diabetic?
Shouldn't they
have been excluded?
And the answer is no,
because there are also
patients who are pre-diabetic
in this data set, who
have been intentionally
included because we don't
know which of them
are going to go on
to develop type 2 diabetes.
And so this is an indicator that
the patient has been previously
flagged as being pre-diabetic.
And it obviously
makes sense that
would be at the very top of
the predictive variables.
But there are also
many things that
are a little bit less obvious.
For example, here
we see obstructive
sleep apnea and
esophageal reflux
as being chosen by the model
to be predictive of the patient
developing type 2 diabetes.
What we would conjecture is
that those variables, in fact,
act as surrogates for
the patient being obese.
Obesity is very seldom coded
in commercial health insurance
claims.
And so with this
variable, despite the fact
that the patient might be
obese, if this variable is not
observed then patients who
are obese often have what's
called sleep apnea.
So they might stop breathing
for short periods of time
during their sleep.
And so that then would
be a sign of obesity.
So I talked about how
the criteria which
we use to evaluate risk
stratification models
are a little bit different
from the criteria used
to evaluate diagnosis models.
Here I'll tell you one of the
measures that we often use,
and it's called positive
predictive value.
So what we'll do is
look at after you've
learned your model.
Look at the top 100 predictions,
top 1,000 predictions,
top 10,000 predictions,
and look to see
what fraction of those patients
went on to actually develop
type 2 diabetes.
Now of course, this is
done using held up data.
Now the reason why you might be
interested in different levels
is because you might want to
target different interventions
depending on the risk and cost.
For example, a very
low cost intervention--
one of the ones that we did--
was sending a text message
to patients who are suspected
to have high risk of developing
type 2 diabetes.
If they've not been to see their
eye doctor in the last year,
we send them a text
message saying maybe you
want to go see your eye doctor.
Remember, you get
a free eye checkup.
And this is a very
cheap intervention,
and it's a very
subtle intervention.
The reason why it
can be effective
is because patients who
develop type 2 diabetes, once
that diabetes progresses
it leads to something
called diabetic
retinopathy, which
is often caught in an eye exam.
And so that could
be one mechanism
for patients to be diagnosed.
And so since it's so cheap, you
could do it for 10,000 people.
So you take the 10,000
most risky people.
You apply the
intervention for them,
and you look to see
which of those people
actually had developed
diabetes in the future.
In the model that I showed
you, 10% of that population
went on to develop
type 2 diabetes
1 to 3 years from then.
The comparison point I'm
showing you here, this blue bar,
is if you used a
model which is derived
using a very small
number of features,
so not a machine
learning based approach.
And there, only 6%
of the people went on
to develop type 2 diabetes
from the top 10,000.
On the other hand,
other interventions
you might want to do
are much more expensive.
So for example,
you might only be
able to do that
intervention for 100 people
because it costs so much money,
and you have a limited budget
as a health insurer.
And so for those people,
you could ask well,
what is the positive predictive
value of those top 100
predictions?
And here, that was 15%
using the machine learning
based model and less
than half of that using
the more traditional approach.
So I'm going to stop here.
There's a lot more that
I can and will say.
But I'll have to get to it
in next Thursday's lecture,
because I'd like our
guest to come down,
and we will have a
bit of a discussion.
To be clear, this
is the first time
that we've ever had this
type of class interaction
which is why, by the way,
I ran a little bit late.
I hadn't ever done
something like this before.
So it's an experiment.
Let's see what happens.
So, do you say Leonard?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Len's fine.
DAVID SONTAG: Len, OK.
So Len, could you please
introduce yourself?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Sure.
My name is Len D'Avolio.
I'm an assistant professor
at Harvard Medical School.
I am also the CEO and founder
of a company called Sift.
Do you want a little
bit of background or no?
DAVID SONTAG: Yeah, a
little bit of background.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Yeah, so
I've spent probably the last 15
years or so trying to help
health care learn from its data
in new ways.
And of all the fields
that need your help,
I would say health care
for both societal, but also
just from a where we're at
with our ability to use data
standpoint is a great place for
you guys to invest your time.
I've been doing
this for government,
in academia as a researcher,
publishing papers.
I've been doing
this for non-profits
in this country
and a few others.
But every single project
that I've been a part of
has been an effort to bring
in data that has always
been there, but we haven't been
able to learn from until now.
And whether that's
at the VA building
out there, genomic
science infrastructure,
recruiting and enrolling
a million veterans
to donate their
blood and their EMR,
or at Ariadne Labs over out
of Harvard School of Public
Health and the Brigham,
improving childbirth in India--
it's all about how can we get a
little bit better over and over
again to make health care
a better place for folks.
DAVID SONTAG: So tell me,
what is risk stratification
from your perspective?
Defining that I found to be
one of the most difficult parts
of today's lecture.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Well, thank
you for challenging me with it.
[LAUGHTER]
So it's a rather
generic term, and I
think it depends entirely on the
problem you're trying to solve.
And every time I go
at this, you really
have to ground
yourself in the problem
that you're trying to solve.
Risk could be running out of a
medical supply in an operating
room.
Risk could be an Apgar score.
Risk could be from
pre-diabetic to diabetic.
Risk could be an older person
falling down in their home.
So really, what is it to me?
I'm very much caught up
in the tools analogy.
These are wonderful
tools with which
a skilled craftsman surrounded
by others that have skills
could go ahead and solve
very specific problems.
This is a hammer.
It's one that we
spend a lot of time
refining and applying to
solve problems in health care.
DAVID SONTAG: So why don't you
tell us about some of the areas
where your company
has been applying risk
stratification today
at a very high level.
And then we'll choose on of
them to dive a bit deeper into.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Sure.
So the way we
describe what we do
is it's performance improvement.
And I'm just giving you
a little background,
because it'll tell you which
problems I'm focused on.
So it's performance
improvement, and to be candid,
the types of things we like to
improve the performance of are
how do we keep people
out of the hospital.
I'm not going to soapbox
on this too much,
but I think it matters.
Like the example that
you gave that you
were employed to help solve was
by an insurer, and insurance
companies--
there's probably 30
industries in health care.
It's not one industry.
And every one of them has
different and oftentimes
competing incentives.
And so the most
logical application
for these technologies is to
help do preventative things.
But only about, depending on
your math, between 8% and 12%
of health care is
financially incentivized
to do preventative things.
The rest are the
hospitals and the clinics.
And when you think
of health care,
you probably think of those
types of organizations.
They don't typically pay to keep
you out of those facilities.
DAVID SONTAG: So as
a company, you know,
you've got to make
a profit of entry.
So you need to focus
on the ones where
there's a financial incentive.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO:
You focus on where
there's a financial incentive.
And in my case, I wanted
to build a company
where the financial
incentive aligned
with keeping people healthy.
DAVID SONTAG: So what are
some of these examples?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Sure.
So we do a lot with
older populations.
With older
populations, it becomes
very important to understand who
care managers should approach,
because their risk
levels are rising.
A lot of risk stratification,
the old way that you described,
identifies people that are
already at their most acute.
So it's sort of skating to
where the puck has been.
You're getting
attention because you
are at the absolute
peak of your acuity.
We're trying to help care
management organizations find
people that are rising risk.
And even when we do
that, we try to get--
I mean, the power of
these technologies
is to move away from
one size fits all.
So when we think
about rising risk,
we think about in a
behavioral health environment,
it is the rising risk of
an inpatient psychiatric
admission.
That is a very
specific application.
There are things
we can do about it.
As opposed to risk, which
if you think about what's
being done in other
industries, Amazon does not
consider us all consumers.
There are individuals
that are very
likely to react to certain
offers at certain times.
And so we're trying to
bring this sort of more
granular approach into health
care, where we sit with teams
and they're used to just
having generic risk scores.
We're trying to help them think
through which older people are
likely to fall down.
We do work in diabetes
also, so which
children with type 1
diabetes shouldn't just
be scheduled for an
appointment every 3 months,
but you should go
to them right now?
So those are some examples, but
the themes are very consistent.
It's helping organizations
move away from rather generic,
one size fits all toward
what are the more actionable.
So even graduation from care
management, because now you
should be having serious illness
conversations because you're
nearing end of life, or
palliative care referrals,
or hospice referrals.
DAVID SONTAG: OK, so I want
to choose a single one to dive
into.
And I want to choose one that
you've worked on the longest
and where you're already doing
at least the initial parts
of an evaluation of it.
And so I think when we
talked on the phone,
psyche ER was one
of those examples.
Tell us a bit about that one.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Yeah.
Well, I'll just walk you through
the problem to be solved.
DAVID SONTAG: Please, yeah.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Sure.
So we work with a large
behavioral health care
organization.
They are contracted
by health plans,
in effect, to treat people that
have mental health challenges.
And the traditional way
of identifying anyone
for care management is
again, you get a risk score.
When you sort the highest
ranking in terms of odds ratio
variables, it's because
you were already admitted,
because you're older, because
you have more medications.
So they were using
a similar approach,
finding the most acute people.
So the very first thing we
do in all of our engagements
is an understanding.
Where is the
greatest opportunity?
And this has very little to
do with machine learning.
It's just what's
happening today?
Where are these
things happening?
Who is caring for these folks?
Everyone wants to reduce
hospital admissions.
But there's a difference
between hospital admissions
because you're not
taking your meds,
and hospital admissions because
you're addicted to opioids,
and hospital
admissions because you
have chronic complex
bipolar schizophrenia.
So we wanted to first
understand well,
where is the greatest cost?
What types of things are
happening most frequently?
And then you want to have the
clinical team tell you well,
these are the types
of resources we have.
We have people that can
address these issues,
or we have
interventions designed
to solve these problems.
And so you bring together where
is the greatest possible return
on your investment
from both a data
standpoint, a financial
standpoint, but also
and we can do
something about it.
After you do that,
it's only then--
after you have full agreement
from executive teams--
that this is the very
narrow thing that we think
we can address.
Then we begin to
apply machine learning
to try to solve the problem.
DAVID SONTAG: So what
did that funnel lead to?
What did you decide was
the thing to address?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO:
Yeah, it was tried
to reduce inpatient
psychiatric admissions.
And even then, the traditional
way of reducing admissions--
just because it came out
of this tradition of 30 day
readmissions--
has always been thought of
in terms of 30 days out.
But when we
interviewed the teams,
they said actually for
this particular condition
it takes us more like 90 days
to be able to have an impact.
And so that clinical
understanding
mixed with what we have
the resources to address,
that's what steers then the
application of machine learning
to solve a specific problem.
DAVID SONTAG: OK, so psychiatric
inpatient admission-- so these
are patients who come to the
ER for some psychiatric related
problem, and then
when they're in the Er
they're admitted
to the hospital.
They're in the
hospital for anywhere
from a day to a few days.
And you want to
find when are those
going to happen in the future?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Yeah.
DAVID SONTAG: What type of
data is useful for that?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Sure.
You don't have to just get
through the ED, though.
That's the most common, any
unplanned acute admission.
DAVID SONTAG: Got it.
So what kind of data is most
useful for predicting that?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Yeah.
So I think a philosophy
that you all should take
is whatever data
you have, it should
be your competitive advantage
in solving the problem.
And that's different
in the way this
has been done where folks have
made an algorithm somewhere
else, and then they're
coming and telling you,
hey, as long as you have claims
data, then plug in my variables
and I can help you.
Our approach-- and this is sort
of derived from my interest
from the start in solving
the problem and try to make
the tools work faster--
is whatever data
you have, we will
bring it in and consider it.
What ultimately then wins
is dependent on the problem.
But you would not be
surprised to learn that there
is some value in claims data.
You put labs up there.
There's a lot of value in labs.
When it comes to
behavioral health,
and this is where you really
have to understand health care,
it's incredibly under diagnosed.
There is a stigma attached
to carrying diagnosis codes
that would describe you
as having mental health
challenges.
And so claims alone is not
sufficient for that reason.
We find a lot of lift
from care management.
So when you have a care
manager, that care manager
is assessing you and you are
filling out forms and serving
you and giving you
different types of sort
of functional
assessments or activities
of daily living assessments.
That data turns out
to be very powerful.
And then, a dark horse that most
people aren't used to using,
we get a lot of lift
out of the clinicians
whether it's the psychiatrist
or care manager's notes.
So there is value in the written
descriptions of a nurse's
or a care manager's
impressions of what's wrong,
what has been done, what
hasn't been done, and so on.
DAVID SONTAG: So tell me a bit
about the development process.
So you figure out what
you want to predict.
You at least have that in words.
You have your data in one place.
Then what?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Yeah.
Well, you wouldn't be surprised.
The very first
thing we do is just
try to throw a logistic
regression at it.
We want the story to
make sense to begin with,
and we're always
looking for the simplest
solution to the problem.
Then the team sort of iterates
back and forth through based
on how this data looks and
the characteristics of it--
the density, the sparsity--
based on what we
understand about this data,
these guys are in
and out of the plan.
So we may have issues with
data not existing in the time
windows that you had described.
Then they're working their way
through algorithms and feature
selection approaches that
seem to fit for the data
that we have.
DAVID SONTAG: But what error
metrics do you optimize for?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: You're
going to have to ask them.
It's been too long.
DAVID SONTAG: OK.
[LAUGHTER]
LEONARD D'AVOLIO:
I'm 10 years out
of being allowed to write code.
But yeah, then it's
an iterative process
where we have to be--
this is a big deal.
We have to be able to translate.
We do positive predictive
value, obviously.
And I like the way you describe
that, because a lot of folks
that have been trained in
statistics for medicine,
whether it's
epidemiology or the like,
are always looking for an r
squared or an area under ROC.
And we have to help them
understand that you can only
care for so many people.
So you don't really care
what the area under ROC
is for a population of, for this
client, 300,000 in the one plan
that we were serving.
You really care about
for the top 100 or 200,
and really that number should be
derived based on your capacity.
DAVID SONTAG: Yeah.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: So if I can
give you 7 out of 10 for 100,
you might go knock
on their door.
But for, let's say, between
1,000 and 2,000 that number
goes down to 4 out of 10.
Maybe you should go with a
less expensive intervention.
Huge education
component, helping people
understand what they're seeing
and how to interpret it,
and helping them
connect it back to what
they're going to do with it.
And then I think probably,
in courses to follow,
you'll go into all
of the challenges
with interpretability
and the like.
But they all exist.
DAVID SONTAG: So tell me a
bit about how it's deployed.
So once you build a model,
how do you get your client
to start using it?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Yeah.
So you don't start getting them
ready when the model's ready.
I've learned the hard way that's
far too late to involve them
in the process.
And in fact, the one bullet
you had up here that I didn't
completely agree
with was this idea
that these approaches are
easier to plug into a workflow.
Putting a number into an
electronic health record
may be easier.
But when I think
workflow, it's not
just that the number
appears at the right time.
It's the culture of getting--
put it this way.
These care managers have spent
the last 20, 30 years learning
who needs their help, and
everything about their training
and their experience is to
care for the people that
are most acute.
All of the red
flags are going off.
And here comes a bunch of
nerds and computer science
people that are
suggesting that no,
rather than your
intuition and experience
of 30 years you should trust
what a computer says to do.
DAVID SONTAG: So
there are two parts
I want to understand better.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Sure.
DAVID SONTAG: First, how
you deal with that problem,
and second, I
actually am curious
about the technical details.
Do you give them predictions
on a piece of paper?
Do you use APIs?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Yeah.
Well, let me answer
the technical one first
because it's a faster answer.
You remember at the
beginning of this,
I said health care
is pretty immature
from a technical standpoint?
So it's never a piece
of paper, but it
can be an Excel spreadsheet
delivered via secure FTP
once a month, because
that's all they're
able to take right now based
on their state of affairs.
It can be a real
time call to an API.
What we learn to do informing a
company serving health care is
do not create a new interface.
Do not create a new log in.
Accommodate whatever
workflow and systems
they already have in place.
So build for flexibility
as opposed to giving them
something else to log into.
You have very little time.
And the other
thing is clinicians
hate their information
technology.
They love their phones, but they
hate what their organization
forces them to use.
Now that may be a
gross generalization,
but I don't think
it's too far off.
Data is sort of a
four letter word.
DAVID SONTAG: So
over the last week,
the students have been
learning about things like FHIR
and so on.
Are these any of the
APIs that you use?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: No.
So those are technologies
with enormous potential.
You put up a paper that
described a risk stratification
algorithm from 1984.
That paper, I'm sure, was
supported with evidence
that it could make
a big difference.
I'm getting awfully close to
standing on a soapbox again,
but you have to understand
that health care is paid for
based on delivering care.
And the more complex the care
is, the more you get paid.
And I'm not telling you this,
I'm kind of sharing with them.
You know that.
So the idea that a
technology like FHIR
would open up EHRs
to allow people
to just kind of drop
things in or out,
thereby taking away the monopoly
that the electronic health
records have--
these are tough investments for
the electronic health record
vendor to make.
They're being forced by
the federal government.
And they saw the writing on the
wall, so they're moving ahead.
And there's great
examples coming out
of Children's, Ken
Mandl and the like,
where some progress
has been made.
But I live in right now, I
have to get this done inside
of the health care of today.
And very few of
the organizations
that we not just work with
but would even talk to
are in a position,
like FHIR ready.
In 5 years, I think
I'll be telling you--
DAVID SONTAG: Hopefully
something different, yeah.
All right, so can you briefly
answer that first question
about what do you have to give
around a prediction in order
for it to be acted
upon effectively?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Yes.
So the very first thing
you have to do is--
so we invite the
clinical team to be
part of the project
from the very beginning.
It's just really important.
If you show up with a
prediction, you've lost.
They're part of the team.
Remember, I say
we're triangulating
what they can and
can't do, and what
might matter what might not.
They are literally
part of the team.
And as we're moving through,
how would one evaluate
whether or not this works?
We show them, these are
some of the people we found.
Oh yeah, that makes sense.
I know Mr. Smith.
And so it's a real show and
tell process from the start.
DAVID SONTAG: So once
you get closer to that,
after development phase
has been done, then what?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: After
the development phase,
if you've done a great job
you get away from the show
me what variable mattered
on a per patient basis.
So you can show folks the
odds ratios on a model
is easy enough to produce.
You can show people these
are the features that
matter at the model level.
Where this gets tougher is all
of health care is used to Apgar
scores which are
based on 5 things.
We all know what they are.
And the machine
learning results,
the models that we
have been talking
about in behavioral health--
I think the model
that we're using now
is over 3,700
variables with at least
a little bit of a contribution.
So how do you square up the
culture of 5 to 7 variables?
And in fact, I gave
you the variables
and you ran the hypothesis
testing algorithm
versus more of an
inductive approach,
where thousands of
variables are actually
contributing incrementally.
And it's a double edged
sword, because you could never
show somebody 3,700 variables.
But if you show them 3
or 4, then the answer
is, well that's obvious.
I knew that.
DAVID SONTAG: Right, like the
impaired fasting glucose one.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Yes, exactly.
So really, I just
paid you to tell me
that somebody who has been
admitted is likely to readmit.
You know, that's the challenge.
So striking that
balance between--
really, it's education
more than anything,
because I don't think
that an algorithm created
that uses 3,700 variables can
then be turned into decision
support where it can
present you 2 or 3 that
you could rely upon and then
make informed decisions.
And part of the
education process
is we also say forget
about the number.
If I were to give you this
person, what would you do next?
And the answer is always, well
I would look at their chart.
The analogy we use that we
find is helpful is this is GPS,
right?
GPS isn't going to give you like
a magic, underground highway
that we didn't know about.
It's going to suggest the roads
that you're familiar with.
The advantage it has
is that unlike you
in the car as you're driving,
it's just aware of more
than you are and it can do
the math a little bit faster
than you can.
And so it's going to
give you a suggestion,
and it's going to tell
you more often than not,
in your situation, I'm going
to save you a few minutes.
DAVID SONTAG: Yeah.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Now
you're still the driver.
You could still decide to
take 93 South and so be it.
It could be that the GPS
is not aware of the fact
that you really like the view on
Memorial Drive versus Storrow,
and so you're going to do that.
And so we try to help people
understand that it just
has access to a little
bit more than you do,
and it's going to get you
there a little bit faster.
DAVID SONTAG: All right,
I'm going to stop you here
because I want to leave
some time for some questions
from the audience.
So I'll make the
following request.
Try to keep it to
quick responses
so we can get to as many
questions as we can.
AUDIENCE: How much
is there a worry
that certain demographic
groups are under diagnosed
and have less access to care?
And then, would have a
lower risk edification,
and then potentially
be de-prioritized?
How do you think
about adjusting that?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Yeah, so
that was a great question.
I'll try to answer it very fast.
DAVID SONTAG: And could
you repeat the question
as quickly as possible as well?
[LAUGHTER]
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Yeah.
I mean, models can be
biased by experience.
And do you worry about
smaller size populations
being overlooked?
Safe to say, is that fair?
DAVID SONTAG: And the question
was also about the training
data that you used.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Well,
that's what I implied.
DAVID SONTAG: Yeah, OK.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: OK.
So all right, this work we're
doing in behavioral health--
and we've done this in a
few other environments--
if there is a different
demographic for which you would
do something different and they
may be lost in the shuffle,
we do bring that
to their attention.
DAVID SONTAG: Next question!
Is there someone
in the back there?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO:
You went too fast.
DAVID SONTAG: OK, over here.
AUDIENCE: How do you
evaluate [INAUDIBLE]??
Would you be
willing to sacrifice
the data of [INAUDIBLE] to
re-approve the [INAUDIBLE]??
DAVID SONTAG: I'm going
to repeat the question.
You talked about how it's like
reading tea leaves to just
show a couple of
the top features
anyway from a linear model.
So why not just get rid of
all that interpretability
altogether?
Does that open the door to
that possibility for you?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: You're
saying get rid of all
the interpretability.
I think the question was are
you willing to trade performance
for interpretability.
DAVID SONTAG: Yes.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: And that
could be an answer to it.
Just throw it out.
So if I can get our
partners to the point
where they truly understand
what we're doing here
and they have been part
of evaluating the model,
success is when
they don't need to--
on a per patient, who
needs my help basis--
see the 3,000 variables.
But that does mean that as
you're building the model,
you will show them the patients.
You will show them
the variables.
So that's what I
try to walk them to.
DAVID SONTAG: So it's about
building up trust as you go.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Absolutely.
That being said in
some situations,
depending on whether it's
clinically appropriate--
I mean, if I'm in the
hundredth percentile here,
but interpretability
can get me pretty far,
I'm willing to make that trade.
And that's the difference.
Don't fall in love
with the hammer, right?
Fall in love with
building the home,
and then you're easy
enough to just swap it out.
DAVID SONTAG: Next question!
Over there.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, how
much time do you
spend engaging with
[INAUDIBLE] and physicians
before staring to sort
of build your model.
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: So
actually, first we
spend time with the CEO
and the CFO and the CMO--
chief medical, chief
executive, chief financial.
Because if there isn't at
least a 5 to 1 financial return
for solving this
problem, you will never
make it all the
way down the chain
to doing something that matters.
And so what I have learned
is the math is fantastic.
We can model all
sorts of fun things.
But if I can't figure out how
it makes them or saves them--
we have like a $5
million mark, right?
For the size of
our company, if I
can't help you make 5 million,
I know you won't pay me.
So we start there.
As soon as we have
figured out that there
is money to be made or
saved in getting these folks
the right care at
the right time,
then yes the clinicians
are on the team.
We have what's called a working
group-- project manager,
clinical lead, someone
who's liaison to the data.
We have a team and a
communication structure
that embeds the clinician.
And we have clinicians
on the team.
DAVID SONTAG: I think you'll
find in many different settings
that's what it
really takes to get
machine learning implemented.
You have to have working groups
of administration, clinicians,
users, and engineers,
and others.
Over here there's a question.
AUDIENCE: Actually, it's a
question for both of you,
so about the data connection.
So I know as people, we try
to connect all kinds of data
to train the machine
learning model.
But when you have some
preliminary model,
can you have some
insights to guide
you to target certain
data, so that you
can know that this
new information can
be very informative
for prediction tasks
or even design data experiments?
DAVID SONTAG: So I'll
repeat the question.
Sometimes we don't already
have the data we want.
Could we use data
driven approaches
to find what data we should get?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: So we're
doing this right now.
There's a popular thing
in the medical industry.
Everyone's really fired up about
social determinants of health,
and so that has been branded
and marketed and sold.
And so now customers are
saying to us, well hey,
do you have social
determinants of health data?
And that's interesting to
me, because they've never
looked at anything but claims.
And now they're suggesting
go buy a third party data
set which may not add more
value than simply having the zip
code.
And we say of course, we
can bring in new data.
We bring in weather pattern.
We bring in all
kinds of funny data
when the problem calls for it.
That's the easy part.
The real challenge
is will it add value?
Should we invest our time
and energy in doing this?
So if you've got all kinds of
fantastic data, run with it
and then see where
you fall short.
The data just doesn't tell
you, now go out and get
a different type of data.
If the performance is
low clinically and based
on intuition, it makes sense
that another data source
may boost.
Then we'll try it.
If it's free, we'll
try it quicker.
If it costs money, we'll
talk to the client about it.
DAVID SONTAG: For both of
those, I'll give you my answer
to that question.
If you have a high dimensional
enough starting place,
often that can give you a
hint of where to go next.
So in the example
I showed you there,
even though obesity is very
seldom coded in claims data,
we saw that it still showed
up as a useful feature, right?
So that then hints
to us, well maybe
if we got higher
quality obesity data
it would be an
even better model.
And so sometimes you can
use that type of trick.
There is a question over here.
AUDIENCE: We use
codes to [INAUDIBLE]
by calculating how
much the hospital will
gain by limiting [INAUDIBLE]?
DAVID SONTAG: OK, so this is
going to be the last question
that we're going to end on.
And it really has to do with
one of evaluation and thinking
about the impact of
an intervention based
on their predictions.
How much does that causal
effect show up in both the way
that you formalize
problems, then evaluate
the effect of your predictions?
LEONARD D'AVOLIO: Yeah.
So the most important
thing to know
is no customer will ever pay
you for a positive predictive
value.
They don't care, right?
They care about will you
help them save or make money
solving a problem.
So cost effectiveness
starts at the beginning.
But the nice thing about a
positive predictive value
approach-- and there's
so much literature
that can tell you what does the
average cost of certain things
having happened.
So the very first part of any
engagement for us is well,
you guys are here.
This is the cost of being there.
If you improved by 10%, if
we can get approval to that,
then we start to model.
And we say well look, of the
top 100 people 70 of them
are the right people.
Multiply that by
the potential cost.
If you think you can prevent
10 of those terrible things
from occurring, that's
worth this much.
So cost effectiveness
data is at the start.
It's in the modeling stage.
And then at the end,
we never show them
how good we did at predicting.
We show them the baseline.
We say baseline
activities outcomes--
where were you,
what are you doing,
and then did it
make a difference.
And the last part is always
in dollars and cents, too.
DAVID SONTAG: Although Len
didn't mention it here,
he also does quite
some work when
trying to think through
this causal effect.
And we talked about how you
use propensity matching,
for example, in your work.
We won't be able to get into
that in today's discussion,
but we'll come back
to those questions
when we talk about causal
inference in a few weeks.
That's all for today, thanks.
[APPLAUSE]